Finding Aid for Helmecke family papers, 1908-1913
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Helmecke family papers 1908-1913
Helmecke family.
0.3 linear feet
861026 Aa 2
Helmecke family of Grand Rapids, Michigan. Letters from Carl Albert Helmecke and his sister Marie Gertrud Helmecke while students at the University of Michigan; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Carl A. Helmecke (donor no. 7135 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Helmecke family of Grand Rapids had two members who attended the University of Michigan. Carl Albert Helmecke was a 1912 graduate of the College of LS&A. He received his master's degree in 1913. His sister, Marie Gertrud Helmecke received her A.B. degree in 1914.
The collection consists primarily of letters (in German) written to family and friends from Carl A. Helmeck and his sister Marie Gertrud Helmecke while attending the University of Michigan. The letters of Carl Helmecke date from 1908 to 1913 and include some letters written while attending a summer class in Dijon, France in 1911 and while employed as a tutor in Florida in 1913. The collection also includes some photographs and memorabilia from the period when attending the University.
Subjects:
Deutscher Verein (University of Michigan).; Women--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; University of Michigan. Cercle Français.; University of Michigan--Students--Correspondence.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Helmecke, Carl Albert.; University of Michigan. Cross Country Club.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Engineering. Class of 1912.
Contributors:
Helmecke, Carl Albert.; Helmecke, Marie Gertrud.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - Carl Albert Helmecke
    - 1908-1912 (Box 1)
      (52 letters written while a student at the University of Michigan)
    - July-August 1911 (Box 1)
      (13 letters regarding summer term at Dijon, France)
    - January-April 1913 (Box 1)
      (16 letters written while tutoring a wealthy young man in Florida)
  - Marie Gertrud Helmecke
    - 1911-1912 (Box 1)
      (ca. 70 letters written while a student at the University of Michigan)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia and Photographs
  - Photograph of Carl Helmecke, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Postcards of University of Michigan, Country Club, 1908/09 and Engineering Class of 1912 taken in 1908 (Box 1)
  - Anthropometric charts (Box 1)
  - YMCA handbook (Box 1)
  - Cloth flag with numerals "47" in University of Michigan colors (Box 1)
  - Membership cards (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)